Finding Aid for William Dodd Robinson Papers 1933-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William Dodd Robinson Papers 1933-1989, 1933-1976
Robinson, William Dodd, 1911-1988.
2.5 linear feet
Professor of internal medicine at the University of Michigan; head of the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (RARU) at the university. Papers relating to Robinson's career as doctor and professor of arthritis and rheumatology; includes material on work at the University of Michigan, Vanderbilt University, and the Rockefeller Foundation; correspondence, research projects, lecture materials, reports, meeting minutes, professional activities, awards and honors, papers, and visual materials; also correspondence and other miscellaneous materials relating to Louis Harry Newburgh.
90147 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by David W. Robinson, MD (Donor no. 7743 ) in 1989.
The collection is open for research.
William Dodd Robinson (1911-1988) received his A.B. degree from Albion College (Albion, MI) and his M.D. degree from the University of Michigan, cum laude, in 1934. He continued at the University of Michigan for his graduate training as an instructor in medicine (1936-1938) and as a research fellow in medicine (1938-1940). He then worked with the Rockefeller Foundation in the International Health Division at the following locations: as a Special Fellow Vanderbilt University (Nashville, TN) where he worked on the TVA Konnarock Project; as a member of the Health Commission to Europe supervising a nutrition survey in Madrid, Spain (1941); and as a staff member serving in Mexico (1941-1943) where he was in charge of developing a nutrition section in the Mexican Federal Department of Health. Upon leaving the Rockefeller Foundation in 1943 he went to Vanderbilt University, where he was an instructor in medicine and in charge of the Investigative Section of the Tennessee-Vanderbilt Nutrition Project until 1944.
Robinson returned to the University of Michigan in 1944 as an assistant professor of internal medicine. In 1946 he became an associate professor and in 1952 was made a full professor. In 1958 Robinson was appointed chairman of the Department of Internal Medicine, a post he held until 1975.
During his time at the University of Michigan, Robinson served in many capacities. One of the most noted was his work with the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (RARU) of which he was head from 1944 to 1953. He continued as a consultant to the RARU until his retirement in 1979. Robinson also held many University of Michigan Medical School and Hospital committee positions, such as the chairmanship of the Policy and Executive Committee of the Senior Medical Staff, Executive Committee of the Medical School. In addition, Robinson held many committee and board positions of professional societies which are detailed on the curriculum vitae in this collection.
William Dodd Robinson's papers have been arranged into four series: University of Michigan; Research Projects; Professional Activities; and General Materials.
Subjects:
Medicine--Study and teaching.; Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (University of Michigan); Robinson, William Dodd, 1911-1988.; Rockefeller Foundation. International Health Division.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Internal Medicine.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; Newburgh, Louis Harry, 1883-1956.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Laboratories--Michigan.; Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (University of Michigan); Robinson, William Dodd, 1911-1988.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Medical School. Class of 1934.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- University of Michigan
  The University of Michigan series reflects Robinson's activities with the University of Michigan during the years 1937-1985. The files have been placed in alphabetical order, and then chronologically. Notable within this series are the files relating to Robinson's association with the Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (RARU) materials and his lecture materials.
  The RARU materials include correspondence (1937-1950), general materials, personnel files, annual reports (1937-1966), and a slide collection list. These items follow the development of the RARU and Robinson's role in it along with many of his colleagues.
  Robinson kept his lecture notes for the courses he taught at the University of Michigan Medical School, at both the graduate and post-graduate levels. These lecture notes are arranged alphabetically. Most are in outline, yet they indicate the form and content of Robinson's lectures. Unfortunately only a few of his lectures are dated.
  Other materials in this series include Robinson's role in establishing the Periodic Health Appraisal Unit (PHAU); the Arthritis Center and Clinic materials; Rheumatology Division meeting minutes; and a curriculum module for family practice that Robinson devised for the University of Michigan.
  - Academic Personnel Activities Report September 1977-August 1978 (Box 1)
  - Arthritis Center Operating Committee, Minutes 1979-1981 (Box 1)
  - Arthritis Clinic 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Arthritis Clinic Evaluation 1978 (Box 1)
  - Arthritis Unit 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - A Curriculum Module for Family Practice Residents and Extramural Internal Medicine Residents 1980 (Box 1)
  - Freda vs. U-M, et al. 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Periodic Health Appraisal Unit (PHAU)
    - Advisory Committee Meeting Minutes 1976-1981 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 1)
  - Programmed Medical History Cost Assessment 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Rackham Arthritis Research Unit (RARU)
    - Correspondence
      - 1937 (Box 1)
      - 1938 (Box 1)
      - 1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940 (Box 1)
      - 1944-1950 (Box 1)
    - Stipulations of agreement 1937-1938 (Box 1)
    - Special funds 1946-1953 (Box 1)
    - Personnel files 1938 (Box 1)
    - Slide Collection List (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports
      - 1937-1955 (Box 1)
      - 1955-1962 (Box 1)
      - 1963-1964, 1965-1966 (Box 1)
  - Rheumatology Division, Meeting minutes 1985 (Box 1)
  - Lecture Materials
    - Abdominal Rheumatism (Box 1)
    - Ascorbic Acid and Adrenal Cortex (Box 1)
    - Differential Diagnosis & Treatment of Joint Disease (Box 1)
    - Epidemiology of Rheumatoid Arthritis (Box 1)
    - Gout (Box 1)
    - Joint Inflammation, Post Graduate Talks May 1965-July 1966 (Box 1)
    - Joints in Gastrointestinal Disease (Box 1)
    - Nutrition (Section MTIII) (Box 1)
    - Nutrition and Aging (Box 1)
    - Nutritional Assessment (Box 1)
    - Nutritional Deficiencies (Box 1)
    - Nutrition and Health (Box 1)
    - Nutrition Teaching to Junior Section (Box 1)
    - Parthogenesis of Vitamin Deficiency and Diagnosis (Box 1)
    - Physical Diagnosis (Box 1)
  - Lecture Materials
    - Post Graduate Courses in Arthritis & Rheumatism (Box 1)
    - Purine Metabolism (Box 1)
    - Quantitative Undernutrition (Box 1)
    - Restoration of Nutritional Balance (Box 1)
    - Rheumatic Diseases (Box 1)
    - Rheumatism (Lay Talk) (Box 1)
    - Rheumatology--The University of Michigan Department of Post Graduate Medicine 1963 (Box 1)
    - Ruhr Miners Survey (Box 1)
    - Skin Biochemistry (Box 1)
    - Steroid Therapy--Usefulness and Limitations (Box 1)
    - Undernutrition (Box 1)
    - Viscosity--Physical Chemistry (Box 1)
    - Vitamin Deficiency--Jr. Lecture (Box 1)
    - Vitamin E & Anti-Stiffness Factor--Myopathies (Box 1)
    - Vitamin Preparations (Box 1)
    - Vitamins (Box 1)
    - Your Health After Forty (Lay Talk) (Box 1)
- Research Projects
  Research Projects is comprised of both correspondence and reports on Robinson's research projects during the years 1941-1976, although the bulk dates from 1941-1960. These include the graduate training research Robinson did with the Rockefeller Foundation's International Health Division during the period 1941-1944: nutrition survey in Madrid, Spain (1941); and the TVA Konnarock Project with Vanderbilt University (1943-1944) and Mexico (1941-1943). Other research materials pertain to the work Robinson conducted on nutrition while in Brazil (1956), Ecuador (1958), Caracas, Venezuela (1960), and the Tecumseh (MI) project (1976). There are also files on the work Robinson did as consultant to the U.S. Surgeon General with the U.S. Army for nutrition surveys in 1945 and as a clinician on ration trials in 1946, both in Germany. Robinson kept some correspondence with the project materials and other correspondence in his correspondence files, thus it is important to look here and in General Materials.
  - Brazil 1956 (Box 1)
  - Caracas, Venezuela 1960 (Box 1)
  - Ecuador 1958 (Box 1)
  - Germany, U.S. Army 1945 (Box 1)
  - Madrid, Spain 1941 (Box 1)
  - Nashville TN, Konnarock Project
    - 1943-1944 (Box 1)
    - 1944, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Tecumseh Project 1976 (Box 1)
- Professional Activities
  Professional Activities: This series includes correspondence, meeting minutes, and reports and evaluations of professional organizations and activities in which Robinson was involved. The materials are arranged in alphabetical order by name of organization because Robinson was often involved at the same time in many organizations. There are no complete files of the many organizations with which Robinson was involved, but rather, Robinson kept materials which showed his involvement in these organizations. Most significant are the records of the Arthritis and Rheumatism Association (ARA). Robinson was president for the year 1956-1957, and was extremely active in the ARA throughout his career. He was instrumental in establishing the Arthritis and Rheumatism Association Journal; the founding of this journal caused a debate within the medical profession as other medical journals feared that the establishment of a journal devoted wholly to arthritis and rheumatism would not be a positive move for a variety of reasons. This debate generated a great deal of correspondence.
  There is also material regarding Robinson's participation in conferences at which he lectured. Copies or outlines of these lectures are included as are articles written for the Encyclopedia Americana in 1957 and 1958, and two case studies of Robinson's arthritic and rheumatic patients that seem to have been especially important for Robinson's work.
  - American Board of Internal Medicine, Minutes of Board of Governors Meeting 1975-1980 (Box 2)
  - American College of Physicians 1980 (Box 2)
  - American Rheumatism Association
    - Journal
      - Debate 1954-1957 (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1955-1957 (Box 2)
      - Cooperation with Annals 1956 (Box 2)
      - Journal 1957 (Box 2)
    - Conference on Comparative Pathology of Arthritis and Rheumatism 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Proposed Rules of Procedure 1980 (Box 2)
  - Association of Former Chairmen of Medicine (AFCM) 1976-1977 (Box 2)
  - Case Studies
    - 1941-1949 (Box 2)
    - 1974-1977 (Box 2)
  - Central Rheumatism Association 1957 (Box 2)
  - Cryoglobulin and Sjogren's Syndrome 1977 (Box 2)
  - Encyclopedia Americana, Arthritis Articles 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - International Congress on Rheumatic Diseases 1957 (Box 2)
  - International Forum Article 1954-1956 (Box 2)
  - Lilly Research Laboratories, Connective Tissue Conference 1950-1954 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Chapter of the Arthritis Foundation (MCAF)
    - Correspondence 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - Rules and Procedures 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Michigan Rheumatism Society 1972 (Box 2)
  - Michigan State Medical Society 1960 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Conference On Rheumatic Diseases 1954 (Box 2)
  - National Society of Clinical Rheumatologists
    - 1976-1987 (Box 2)
    - Constitution (Box 2)
  - University of Minnesota Continuation Course in Arthritis and Physical Medicine 1958 (Box 2)
  - Vietnam Medical School Project, Final Report 1975 (Box 2)
- General Materials
  General Materials: This series is comprised of ten subseries: awards and honors; biographical; general correspondence (1933-1989); licenses and certificates; Louis Harry Newburgh files; Dwight D. Eisenhower Library Oral History Project (1978); papers; photographs; and slides.
  The biographical materials include an exhaustive curriculum vitae of William Dodd Robinson and a bibliography of all articles and papers he wrote.
  The General Correspondence is arranged chronologically from 1933 to 1989. The correspondence as a whole is not consistent because Robinson divided his files according to subject and filed correspondence in several places. As a result there is often correspondence in both topical as well as in the correspondence files. This is also the reason there is a gap from 1958 to 1975 in the correspondence files. Researchers should look in the topical files for correspondence to these years.
  The Louis Harry Newburgh files have been retained because Newburgh had an influence on Robinson's career, and Newburgh was quite prominent in the fields of arthritis and rheumatology. Robinson was involved in helping to write a biography of Newburgh after Newburgh's death; these materials were probably part of Robinson's research.
  In 1978 the Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library interviewed Robinson as part of their Oral History Project. A transcript of this interview is here as well as some correspondence. Robinson was asked to participate in this project as he was an individual whose career coincided with the Eisenhower Administration, and someone who had a definite impact on the field of nutrition, specifically metabolic diseases. This interview provides a rather detailed description of Robinson's career through Robinson's eyes.
  The photographs are divided into departmental photographs, research and case study photographs, portraits, and personal photographs. Some are labelled. There are some slides that Robinson used for lectures and presentations.
  - Awards and Honors (Box 2)
  - Biographical and Bibliographical Information (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1933-1943 (Box 2)
    - 1944-1947 (Box 2)
    - 1948-1958 (Box 2)
    - 1975-1984 (Box 2)
  - Licenses and Certificates (Box 2)
  - Louis Harry Newburgh Files, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Oral History Project, Dwight D. Eisenhower Presidential Library 1976-1979 (Box 2)
  - Arthritis Papers, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Textbook Chapters, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Nicaragua, NSCR February 1978 (Box 3)
    - Rackham Arthritis Research Unit 1939-1960s (Box 3)
    - Madrid circa 1941 (Box 3)
    - Departmental (Box 3)
    - Portraits (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Reunions (Box 3)
    - Louis Harry Newburgh (Box 3)
  - Slides and Negatives (Box 3)